it's Dr. Donna McMahon.
Continuing the pediatric
cardiology considerations,
Dr. Chan presented
parts one and two and I
am presenting part three.
I have my contact
information on the
slide in the
PowerPoint and I hope
that you reach out
with any questions.
Hopefully by the time
you are listening to this
presentation you've already
read and completed the
assignments on the CPG.
I just wanted to let you
know there's a QR code
that goes directly to the
Nelson's Pediatrics Essential
and you can look up the
chapter number or numbers.
Also, I've included on
the CPG an AI-generated
brick from my PowerPoint.
Here are the
resources I used for
this presentation,
and I hope that the
ScholarRx brick
was helpful to you.
Let's start with our
first patient. We
have an 18-year-old
girl who presents with
fainting on her
first day of college.
The HPI. She's 18. She
presents to the College Health
Center because of a
fainting spell while at a
morning class. She was rushing
to her 8 a.m. class after
she missed her alarm. She
got out of bed, brushed
her teeth, washed her face,
got dressed, ran to class.
While she was in her seat,
she felt lightheaded,
was started to perspire,
and then had loss of
consciousness. She passed
out for approximately one
minute, was observed by her
classmates, and her professor
intervened and walked
the student over to the
health center. No significant
past medical history,
surgical history. Her
immunizations are up to date.
She doesn't take any
medications. Her social history,
she denies any drugs or
tobacco use, but admits
to drinking alcohol with
friends the night before.
Physical examination,
she's afebrile.
Her heart rate is
elevated at a rate of 120.
Respiratory rate is
normal, 18, 120 pounds,
64 inches tall. Blood
pressure, a little
elevated, 132 over 72 with
a normal pulse oximeter
reading of 98%. She's
well appearing in
no distress, but appears
a little fatigued.
Her head, eyes, ears,
nose, and throat were
within normal limits.
Her lungs were clear to
auscultation without
rails, ronchi, or wheezes.
Her cardiac exam, she
had increased rate,
but regular rhythm and
no murmurs. Her abdomen
was within normal
limits, as were her upper
lower extremity exam
and her neuro exam.
What do you think the cause
of her syncope could be from?
Orthostatic hypotension,
a psychogenic cause,
a long QT interval,
vasovagal cause,
or hypoglycemia.
if you said orthostatic
hypotension you are correct
what if you obtained an EKG
and this is what you got
back what would you say then
would you still say this
was vasovagal no you would
take a look at this EKG
and you would see that
there is a prolonged period
between the Q and the T wave,
and you can see it really
well in leads 1, 2, and 3,
of course the entire EKG,
but that's where you see
a prolonged Q-T interval.
What is syncope?
It's an involuntary loss of
posture and consciousness,
and there are many causes
and so I've listed some
of them here for you vasovagal
that's the interruption
of normal central vasomotor
tone which leads to
arteriolar vasodilation
which leads to hypotension
which leads to decreased
cerebral perfusion pressure
it's considered the common
faint can be more common
after fasting anxiety
fright or surprise then
there's vago vagal and that
is when the vagus nerve is
stimulated causing extreme
bradycardia in the old
days when a baby was born
we typically suction the
posterior pharynx for
mucus or meconium and would
stimulate the vagus nerve,
causing a transient bradycardia
where the baby would lose
consciousness or tone.
Cardiac causes, usually
associated with heart
lesions that cause
obstruction to the left-sided
blood flow, for example,
aortic stenosis. Arrhythmogenic
causes, those are
arrhythmias, and the
example we talked about
was the long QT syndrome.
Orthostatic,
that's our patient.
Failure of vascular compensatory
responses to postural
changes. You get up,
your blood pressure drops
when it's supposed to
increase, and you pass out.
Our patient was dehydrated.
We continue on with
other causes, seizure
disorders, metabolic reasons
like hypoglycemia, and
behavioral, hysterical
syncope, now it's
referred to as psychogenic
pseudosyncope, breath
holding, or hyperventilation.
let's take a second to
talk about the long qt
syndrome it's an example
of an arrhythmogenic cause
of syncope it's a
myocardial repolarization
disorder it can progress
to ventricular arrhythmias
torsade de point and
then that leads to the
syncope it can also lead
to sudden death not good.
The QT interval is
longer, usually, than 0.46
seconds, so pretty long. It
can be congenital or acquired,
and males are less
affected than females. The
congenital examples are
Romano-Ward syndrome where
you have normal hearing and
it's autosomal dominant.
The dural and Lang
-Nielsen syndrome where you
have deafness and it's
autosomal recessive. Then
there's Anderson-Tawil
syndrome which is autosomal
dominant and Timothy
syndrome which is sporadic.
Ion channel disturbances,
mutations in genes responsible
for calcium, potassium,
and sodium are implicated
in the congenital cause
of long QT syndrome.
Acquired causes can be drugs,
electrolyte disturbances,
underlying diseases
like hypothyroidism, And
you may have a history
or a family history
of congenital deafness
and or sudden death.
How do we work these kids up?
Well, most common causes
in pediatrics are vasovagal
or non-cardiogenic
syncopal episodes, and they
last less than one minute.
We use our history to our
advantage. if there's
incontinence loss of urine or
loss of stool it's probably
a seizure that would
be non-cardiac if you if the
patient had prior cardiac
surgery it's probably
an arrhythmia if there's
a family history of deafness
or sudden death probably
an arrhythmia if it's
exercise induced it could
be arrhythmia or it could
be an outflow obstruction
like hypertrophic sub aortic
stenosis longer duration
the the patient has is
unconscious for a longer
period of time that can
be a structural cardiac or
an arrhythmia and if it's
a witness cardiac arrest
then you can probably rule
out a neurogenic cause.
The treatment seems
pretty simple.
You need to treat
the underlying cause,
but you have to figure
out the underlying
cause. So the treatment's easy,
but the diagnosis
could be difficult.
Reassurance most of
the time for these
patients, increase their fluid
intake and increase
their salt intake.
Case number two, we
have a seven-year
-old female with a
red swollen knee.
Before we discuss our
patient in case number two,
I just want to say that
if you noticed that in
different parts of this
presentation I have a different
haircut or length or
glasses or outfit or office
setting, you are correct
and great observation. So
let's get to our seven
-year-old girl who presents
for her first visit to
the pediatrician's office
since arriving in the US.
Three weeks ago she presented
to border control in Texas
with a two-day history
of fever to 104 and a sore
throat. She was examined
and symptomatic treatment
was recommended. To
her physical exam she had
enlarged slightly tender
bilateral anterior cervical
lymph nodes. Her oropharynx
was injected and she had
soft palate petechia.
Her rapid strep test
was negative. No throat
culture was sent. She
had an increased heart
rate, normal rhythm.
Lungs were clear with no
rails, ronchi, or
wheezes, and no skin rash.
Today, she comes to you
with a one-week history
of intermittent fleeting
and random knee and
wrist swelling, which is
accompanied by pain and
redness. Mom says she has
decreased activity, she
feels tired, and she
developed a flat pink arm
rash with a pale center
approximately two days
ago. She has no allergies.
She's had no surgery.
Her past medical history
is non-contributory
except for the HPI, and
she's taken Tylenol.
That's the symbol for
acetaminophen for her pain.
Physical examination. Her
heart rate is elevated 130
beats per minute. Her
respiratory rate is elevated at
30 breaths per minute. Her
blood pressure is normal at
110 over 70. She has 100.8
degree Fahrenheit temperature,
which is elevated and
her pulse oximeter is 97
percent which is normal. She's
alert, she's well hydrated,
she's uncomfortable, and
she's quiet. Her H-double
-E-N-T exam is totally non
-contributory. There's no
soft palate petechiae, there's
no tonsillar injection,
no posterior pharyngeal
injection. She has an increased
heart rate and a grade 2
over 6 holosystolic murmur
best heard at the apex, and
her lungs are clear. Her
abdomen was non-contributory,
no hepatosplenomegaly.
Her right knee is warm,
tender, erythematous, swollen,
and has decreased range of
motion secondary to pain.
Neurologic is grossly intact.
We drew some labs. Her
C-reactive protein is
positive. Her erythrocyte
sedimentation rate is
elevated. Her anti
-streptolysin o-titer is
elevated. Her white blood
count is elevated. And
on EKG, she has a first
degree heart block.
And on her chest x-ray,
she has cardiomegaly.
So what do you think she has?
Kawasaki disease,
acute rheumatic fever,
lupus, cardiomyopathy,
juvenile idiopathic arthritis.
If you chose acute rheumatic
fever, you are correct.
Acute rheumatic fever I
believe is well covered
in the brick that is
included in your CPG,
so you don't need
to listen to me talk
about it. If there
are any questions
you know you can
always reach out to me.
How do we treat
rheumatic fever?
Let's back up a little bit.
Our best treatment
is prevention,
preventing it from
ever occurring.
That's why we use antibiotics
to treat a patient with
streptococcal pharyngitis
that pharyngitis will get
better on its own just by
mother nature when we use
antibiotics it does shorten
the course by about two days
but that's not the reason
we use antibiotics we use
antibiotics to prevent
acute rheumatic fever from
occurring in the future once
you're diagnosed with acute
rheumatic fever then you are
put on long-term penicillin
prophylaxis either orally
which is a twice a day
or parenterally intramuscular
and that's once a month
why do we do that it is
to eradicate the strep
and then you can use
NSAIDs non-steroidal anti
-inflammatories with or
without steroids for
the inflammatory reaction
and then you treat
the congestive heart
failure if appropriate and
you treat the valvular
disease as necessary
NSAIDs are a wonderful
group of medications but
they may mask migratory
polyarthritis and so it's
best to use acetaminophen
for strep pharyngitis and
for patients presenting
with possible rheumatic
fever until the diagnosis
is made and then you can
go all out and use
your non-steroidal anti
-inflammatories. Case number
three, we have a six-month-old
male who presents with
irritability, sweating,
decreased feeding and rapid
breathing for two days.
One week ago parents
noted a body rash and that
was followed with a
low-grade fever for two
days. Otherwise no other
complaints. His birth
history is non-contributory.
He's not on any
medications and he has no
significant past medical
or surgical history.
Physical examination.
The infant's
inconsolable, pale, well
-hydrated, well
-developed, and sweating.
The anterior fontanelle
is open and flat.
The vital signs,
afebrile, increased
respiratory rate,
increased heart rate,
and decreased pulse
oximeter. The head,
eyes, ears, nose, throat
exam is unremarkable.
The neck is supple.
Heart rate is increased
with diminished
heart sounds and an S3 present.
Increased respiratory
rate with wheezes
throughout and intercostal
retractions noted.
The abdomen revealed
positive bowel
sounds with hepatosplenomegaly.
The extremities had
decreased peripheral pulses
and the capillary refill
was three seconds.
And on the skin there were no
lesions but just
noted to be pale.
You obtain an EKG and you
see low voltage throughout
the 12 leads in the QRS and
then you have ST segment
depression, his chest x
-ray shows pulmonary edema,
elevated diaphragms,
and cardiomegaly.
What's your diagnosis?
Kawasaki disease,
acute rheumatic fever,
truncus arteriosus,
hypoplastic left
heart syndrome,
or dilated cardiomyopathy.
If you chose dilated
cardiomyopathy, you are correct.
Myocardial diseases, first
we're going to break it
down according to etiology
but we're going to spend
more time on talking about
primary myopathic disease
which is dilated hypertrophic
and restricted or
restrictive cardiomyopathies
so you can break it
down according to etiology
infectious metabolic
infiltrative and ischemic
infectious viral infections,
non-viral infections, and
immunologic, just like we
will talk about in the
future, Kawasaki syndrome,
but that we just spoke
about acute rheumatic fever.
Metabolic, the electrolyte
imbalances, endocrine
system, hypothyroidism,
infant of a diabetic mother,
medications and drugs
cocaine radiation chloroquine
alcohol and then vitamin or
trace metal deficiencies like
selenium carnitine taurine
thiamine infiltrative
causes glycogen storage
diseases amyloidosis sarcoidosis
hemochromatosis neoplasms
and you go polysaccharidosis
and then ischemic causes
those are rare and that can
involve congenital anomalies
of the coronary arteries.
Cardiomyopathy is
a disease of the
myocardium. Usually
you have a large heart
either from more muscle
or a larger cavity.
But let's talk about the
classification. Dilated
cardiomyopathy is the most
common. It can be idiopathic,
infectious, post-infectious,
familial, secondary
to systemic disease or
from cardiotoxic drugs.
Hypertrophic, about
half the patients it's a
familial reason. And then
restrictive. Restrictive
is rare in pediatrics.
It's typically idiopathic
but can be secondary
to a systemic disease.
We're looking again at
primary myopathic disease.
And if you look
based on physiology,
dilated cardiomyopathy is
a systolic dysfunction.
Hypertrophic is a
diastolic dysfunction.
Restrictive is a
If we take a look
at the top left
heart, that is the
normal healthy heart.
Look at the width of the
myocardium and
across the chamber.
We look at this part
on the upper right.
We see a dilated chamber,
thinner myocardium. That is
a dilated cardiomyopathy.
And you may have an atrium
that's a little larger
as well. The bottom left,
if you see here, the chamber
is very small and the
myocardium is hypertrophied.
That is hypertrophic. And
then we have restrictive.
Restrictive, you can
have a normal to mildly
decreased chamber and you can
have normal to hypertrophied
myocardium. Typically,
we see a dilated atrium.
Dilated cardiomyopathy is the
most common in pediatrics.
there's myocyte atrophy,
which increases the left
ventricular cavity, which
decreases the ability to
contract, and you have a low
ejection fraction. It's a
pumping defect, therefore
a systolic defect. Patients
can present with CHF,
decreased cardiac output. You
might have a left bundled
branch block as well if you
find a an identifiable cause
like alcohol intoxication
infection pregnancy
malnutrition you can reverse
it irreversible would be
genetic or a drug induced
like doxy rubicin and
often it's idiopathic
we don't know what's going
on You treat the causative
agent, if you can,
and then you treat the
symptoms, sometimes
requiring a heart transplant.
Mortality rate is 50
% within five years.
Hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy. This
is where the
myocytes are larger.
Therefore, they decrease
the left ventricular
cavity size. It's a
filling defect. There's
not a lot of volume that
you can put in there
because it's all this
muscle around. It's a
filling defect. It's a
diastolic dysfunction.
And it has an
increased ejection
fraction. Because
whatever you put in
there, you can
definitely pump it out.
But you can't get a
whole lot of blood in
there. It's asymptomatic
until you die.
Terrifying.
you can have sudden
death in patients who are
participating in athletics they
have an increased heart rate
from exercise causes an
arrhythmia and you're inside
a path pathologic myocardium
and it can't handle
it treatment is symptomatic
you can do a myomectomy
remove some of that myocardium
a heart transplant and
patients have a five
percent chance each year of
sudden death I don't like
these cardiomyopathies because
the outcomes are not so
great thankfully restrictive
cardiomyopathy is rare it's
a diastolic dysfunction
because of the poor
compliance of the ventricular
walls the ventricular volume
can be normal to mildly
decrease the wall thickness
increased as we saw in earlier
typically there's atrial
enlargement that accompanies
it to how do you treat
it you control the symptoms
and you maintain healthy
blood pressure without
decreasing cardiac output.
Cardiac transplant is
often needed and the
prognosis is poor.
Five-year survival for
these patients is
less than 30 percent.
Case number four, we
have a very unhappy 18
-month-old who's had fever
for the past six days.
Case number four. An 18
-month-old male presents
to your pediatric
office with six days of
fever with a maximum
temperature of 104 degrees
axillary temp, which
is 40 degrees Celsius.
His mom states he has red
eyes and lips, has a rash,
has swollen hands, and a
swollen gland in his neck.
On physical exam, he has
an elevated temp of 104.4
Fahrenheit, elevated heart
rate at 160 beats per
minute, elevated respiratory
rate at 30 breaths per
minute, and his pulse
oximeter is at 96%, which is
acceptable. He's non-toxic
appearing, and he's crying,
but he's consolable in his
mother's arms. He's hot to
touch. He's well hydrated
and well-developed. His
conjunctiva are injected
bilaterally, conjunctiva
injected, but no discharge,
and the rest of his eye exam
is normal. His mouth, he
has no oral ulcers, but he
has an injection, has
injection of the oropharynx.
Tongue is with red
prominent papillae,
and his lips are
red and cracked.
His ears are
normal under the
circumstances. His TMs are pink
because of his elevated
temperature. On his neck, his
neck is supple, phew, probably
not meningitis, but he
has a two by two centimeter
right tonsillar lymph
node that's mobile and non
-tender. He has increased
heart rate, no murmurs,
his lungs are clear, and on
extremities, his hands and
his feet, he has non-pitting
edema. You do a rapid
strep test in the office
and it's negative and his
throat culture is pending.
This child looks sick to
you and because of the
history you decide to obtain
a CBC which shows elevated
white blood count, low
hemoglobin and hematocrit
and he has normal platelets.
His erythrocyte sedimentation
rate is elevated. His
urinalysis shows some
white blood cells, no
bacteria but some protein and
his EKG is only significant
for a sinus tachycardia.
So what do you think is
going on with this patient?
Does he have scarlet fever,
Stevens-Johnson syndrome,
juvenile idiopathic arthritis,
Kawasaki disease, or
acute rheumatic fever?
If you chose Kawasaki
disease, you are correct.
Epidemiology of
Kawasaki disease,
it's a generalized
vasculitis of unknown
etiology. We've been
trying for years to try
to figure it out. We
just haven't come up with
an etiologic agent.
Perhaps it's mimicry
of an infectious agent.
We just don't know.
It has endemic and
epidemic patterns.
Most commonly we see
in the winter and
springtime, more
common in children.
80% of the cases occur
in kids less than eight
years of age, more
common in Asian ancestry,
and it's actually a
leading, one of the leading
causes of acquired
heart disease in kids.
Let's talk about how to
diagnose Kawasaki disease.
There are certain criteria that
fit the typical
Kawasaki diagnosis.
You need fever for
greater than five days,
and fever is defined
as a temperature
of greater than 100
.4 degrees Fahrenheit.
Typically the fever is
much higher than that.
And then you need
four out of the five
of the following. Changes
in the extremities,
changes in the oral
mucosa, a rash,
eye involvement,
and lymph node involvement.
Changes in the extremities.
In the acute phase you
can have erythema and
swelling, edema, of the
hands and the feet. In
the subacute phase that's
further out in the disease
progression, you can have
desquamation or peeling
of those hands and feet.
Changes in the oral mucosa,
you can have cracked red
fissured lips, you can
have an injected pharynx
and oral mucosa, or and
you can have a strawberry
tongue, swelling of the
papilla of the tongue.
The rash can take on
various forms. There's
not a specific rash
that is specific to
Kawasaki disease. If
you have conjunctival
injection, it's bilaterally,
it's not painful,
and you don't have an
exudate, no discharge.
If you have cervical
lymphadenopathy with
this disease, it's
typically unilateral.
And then in addition
you can have
changes in the CBC
and that can be
elevated WBCs, you
can have decreased
RBCs, and early in
the disease your
platelet count can be
normal. Later in the disease
you have thrombocytosis,
increased platelet count.
what are we worried about
coronary artery aneurysms
strawberry tongue
sounds fun I'm
not sure it's very fun to have
so initially kawasaki
disease causes a white
exudate on the tongue
and that's what this is
all this white stuff
and you have enlarged
papilla so you can see
the taste buds and that's
due to erythema and
inflammation then the
white exudate disappears
make it disappear good
and then you have
desquamation along the tongue
surface and that's where
we have a tongue that
starts to look like a
strawberry there are other
diseases that are associated
with the strawberry
tongue scarlet fever group
a beta hemolytic strep
with an enterotoxin
Kawasaki disease, like we're
talking about, and toxic
-like shock syndrome.
This all seems so complicated
because this disease has
three phases. There's an acute
febrile phase, a subacute
phase, and a chronic or
convalescent phase. The
first phase is usually one
to two weeks of illness and
that's where you get necrotizing
arteritis, inflammation
of the arteries. This
is where coronary artery
aneurysms may start to form.
The subacute phase usually
lasts three weeks, and you can
have the subacute or chronic
vasculitis, which can go
on for years. You can have
desquamation, that's of
the skin and of the tongue
and a thrombocytosis elevated
platelet count. Then the
third phase is the chronic
or convalescent phase, and
that can last up to two
months. And that is where the
vasculitis develops smooth
muscle myofibroblasts,
which leads to stenosis
of the vessels.
most symptoms are are in
the acute phase most serious
sequela occur in the
subacute or the chronic phase
and this is why it's
important for early diagnosis
because we want to prevent
the sequela please excuse
the fact that the credits
are at the top of the slide
I just couldn't fit
everything in and have you be
able to see me presenting.
I like this slide. It shows
the clinical manifestations
of Kawasaki disease
divided into acute, subacute,
and the convalescent phase
talking about fever,
arthritis, cardiovascular
problems, myocarditis, and
aneurysm, coronary artery
aneurysm skin changes mucosal
changes cervical adenitis
and thrombocytosis so you
can see when all of these
manifestations occur it's
divided into stages when
we are talking about untreated
kawasaki disease coronary
artery disease stage one
is the first two weeks
you have acute vasculitis
of the coronary arteries.
Stage two is about two to
four weeks after onset. The
vasculitis persists, can
cause weakening of the walls
of the vessels, leading
to the Basilar aneurysms.
Flow decreases with an
increasing diameter. Remember
that in physics, stagnant
blood, because of decreased
blood flow you can have stasis
of blood in the aneurysmal
sacs and that may lead
to thrombosis thrombosis
in coronary arteries may lead
to obstruction of coronary
blood flow not good because
we know when you stop
blood flow through the
coronaries you can get a
myocardial infarction stage
three four to eight weeks after
the onset of the illness
you get artery inflammation
subsiding, but the aneurysms
may persist. And then
stage four, greater than
two months after the onset,
you have scar formation of
these coronary arteries and
calcification with stenosis
and recanalization of
the lumen, also myocardial
fibrosis. 20% of untreated
children will develop coronary
artery disease. Scary.
Very old photos, but this
is a coronary artery.
This is the aneurysm.
This would remain
the diameter. This is
all the aneurysmal sac.
these are cross sections
in section B of the same
vessel and then C is
magnified from the center
so you see the thrombosis
and stenosis and the
recanalization sounds
really bad so how do we
treated first you want
to reduce inflammation
remember in vasculitis is
the first manifestation
so you want to reduce
inflammation to prevent
coronary artery aneurysms
that's the initial therapy
the chronic therapy is
to prevent the coronary
artery thrombosis so
initially ivig The intravenous
immunoglobulin is given
to decrease the immune
response and we have about
an 85% success rate if
you use it within the
first 10 days of symptoms.
In the acute phase,
the anti-inflammatory
phase that we talked
about, you use aspirin
and that reduces systemic
symptoms and it decreases
the risk of aneurysm
formation. I know you're
saying, oh my gosh, Dr.
Goldstein and Dr. Pino
said don't use aspirin
in children, but this
is one of the few cases
that you do use aspirin
in children. The benefit
far outweighs the risk.
And in chronic treatment,
which is the antithrombotic
treatment, you're using
aspirin again, but
you use it at a much lower
dose. You can use TNF
-alpha antibodies and you
can use a second dose of
IVIG. You can add in
steroids for resisting cases.
Well, congratulations,
we've made it through the
cases. Just to summarize
syncope, you must
identify the cause to
prevent subsequent episodes.
Cardiomyopathy is an
intrinsic disease of the
heart muscle and you don't
want to get it. Acute
rheumatic fever is sequela
of strep pharyngitis.
You need the Jones
criteria to diagnose
it. It damages valves
and you require long-term
antibiotic prophylaxis
to prevent recurrences.
Kawasaki disease is
a vasculitis and it's
really a clinical
diagnosis. Our treatment
focuses on coronary artery
aneurysm prevention.
Kid President is one
of my favorites and
I love this quote. If
it doesn't make the
world better, just
don't do it. I think
it's a pretty good
philosophy for for life.
Thank you everyone for
participating in
this presentation.
I hope to see you on
campus and for those
out in Jonesboro, please
feel free to reach
out to me anytime. We
can zoom, we can email,
we can talk to each other
on the phone, but remember
you can always reach out
for any questions or if
you just want to chat
about other things. Don't
forget to fill out the
survey and have a great day.